<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The oration made vnto the French king by the deputies of the Nationall Synode of the Reformed Churches of France, vpon the death of the Marquesse d'Ancre, with the Kings answere therunto, 27. Maij. 1617 Also a discourse of the beginning, progression, actions and behauiour of Cochino, Marquesse d'Ancre, and his wife Galligaia, with his proiects and practises life and death. Compendiously, but more fully expressed then heretofore. Faithfully translated out of the French copie.</title>
            <author>Eglises réformées de France. Synode national.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01190</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11305</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117195</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852410</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852410</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17731</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01190)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17731)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1137:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The oration made vnto the French king by the deputies of the Nationall Synode of the Reformed Churches of France, vpon the death of the Marquesse d'Ancre, with the Kings answere therunto, 27. Maij. 1617 Also a discourse of the beginning, progression, actions and behauiour of Cochino, Marquesse d'Ancre, and his wife Galligaia, with his proiects and practises life and death. Compendiously, but more fully expressed then heretofore. Faithfully translated out of the French copie.</title>
                  <author>Eglises réformées de France. Synode national.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Felix Kyngston for Nathanael Newbery, and are to be sold at his shop vnder S. Peters Church in Cornhill, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts. Part 2 has a caption title: The life, carriage, and progressions of the vnworthie Marshall d'Ancre.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Concini, Concino, --  maréchal d'Ancre, ca. 1575-1617.</term>
               <term>Galigaä, Léonara, ca. 1571-1617.</term>
               <term>Louis --  XIII, --  King of France, 1601-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Church history --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17731:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17731:1"/>
            <p>THE ORATION MADE VNTO THE FRENCH KING BY THE DEPVTIES OF THE
Nationall Synode of the Reformed Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of France, vpon the death of the Marqueſſe</hi> d'Ancre,
<hi>with the Kings anſwere therunto,</hi> 27. <hi>Maij.</hi> 1617.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO,</hi> A DISCOVRSE OF THE BEGINNING, progreſſion,
actions and behauiour of COCHINO, Marqueſſe <hi>d' Ancre,</hi> and his wife
GALLIGAIA, <hi>with his proiects and practiſes life and death,</hi>
Compendiouſly, but more fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed then heretofore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated out of the French Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Felix Kyngſton</hi> for <hi>Nathanael
New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop vnder <hi>S. Peters</hi>
Church in Cornhill, and in Popes-head Alley. 1617.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="oration">
            <pb facs="tcp:17731:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17731:2"/>
            <head>AN ORATION MADE TO THE FRENCH KING, BY THE deputies of the
National Synode, of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches of France; together with his
Maieſties anſwere to the ſame, the 27. of May. 1617.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>THE NATIONALL SYNODE OF <hi>VITRY</hi> in Brittaine, hauing
deputed to his Maieſty the 20. of May, 1617. theſe Reuerend gentlemen,
Piere <hi>Heſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rien,</hi> Paſtour of the Church of Saint Foy, in baſe
Guienne; <hi>Denis</hi> de Bouteroüe, Paſtor of the Church of Grenoble
in Daulphinois; <hi>Albert de Mars,</hi> Eſquire, Lord of Balene, and Ancient
of the Church of Maringues, in high Auergne; and <hi>William Gerard,</hi>
Eſquire, Lord of Mouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſac, Ancient of the Church of Mouſſac in baſe
Languedoc, the 27. of the ſaid moneth, when the Lord <hi>Heſperien</hi>
ſpake to the King in this tenour following:</p>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Behold here proſtrate at your feet, in our perſons, all your
ſubiects that profeſſe the reformed Religion, repreſented in the
Nationall Synode, by your permiſſion, ſummond and aſſembled, and
vnder your Royall authoritie, in the<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17731:3"/>towne of Vitry, which
hath deputed vs towards your Maieſty, to teſtifie vnto you the
extraordinarie paſſions of ioy, which haue and doe poſſeſſe your
ſaid ſubiects, as alſo the ſolemne and vnfained thankeſgiuing which
they haue, and daily doe giue vnto Almighty God, in that they now behold your
preſent eſtate in perfect peace and repoſe, your authority in full force
and vigor, and your Royall perſon in abſolute liberty; and all this, by the
no leſſe noble, then ſage reſolution, which you vndertooke and
executed, for his iuſt puniſhment, that diſturbed your Realme,
ſuppreſſed your authority; and yet which is worſt, expoſed your
perſon to moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perill and danger. Something indeed very
extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary concurred with this action, but ſo as a diuine and miraculous
hand was not alſo heerein wanting; which (as it were) in a moment turned all
the ſtorme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a calme, warre, into peace; feare, into all ſecurity;
danger; into deliuerance; and an odious tyrannie, into a moſt iuſt and
lawfull gouernment. For now (as it were) by a new inauguration of your
Maieſty in the Crowne of France, France her ſelfe now cleerly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes
that ſhe hath a King, and all the world no leſſe apprehends, that there
is a King in France, worthie to raigne and rule. Now, that your Royall ſelfe
holds the raines of the State, all your ſubiects are ready to yeeld you, that
moſt humble obedience &amp; ſubmiſſion which they owe, but more
particularly thoſe of the reformed Religion, who are very prompt and willing,
to offer vp for your ſeruice, their goods, their honours; yea, and their
liues themſelues. And for this effect the Conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and aſſembly;
which deputed vs to your Maieſty was no ſooner met and conuented, but they
ſolemnly ſwore and proteſted, and in the name and behalfe of all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17731:3"/>the reformed Churches within your Realme, enioyned vs;
repreſenting their ſeuerall charges, to proteſt and ſweare in their
names, that we will neuer goe aſide, nor ſtart from that moſt humble
obedience and ſeruice, which (as your naturall ſubiects) wee owe vnto you.
Wherunto we further finde our ſelues more ſtraitly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, by the many
and great benefits that we receiued from the late deceaſed, <hi>Henrie</hi>
the Great, of moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous memory, your renouned Father; by others, which
it hath pleaſed your Maieſty to continue towards vs; and by many more,
which wee daily attend and hope for from you. And though wee firmely beleeue,
that the maintenance of your authority and dignitie, is our beſt ſecuritie;
and the eſtabliſhment of your Crowne, our peace and quiet: yet we deeme our
ſelues hereunto yet more neerly bound by the bond of our Religion, and
conſciences, which conformable to the holy Scriptures, daily teach vs, that
wee muſt bee ſubiect to all ſuperior powers; and that the reſiſting
of them, is but an euident oppoſition to Gods will and ordinance: who (we
know) hath elected, and ſeated you in your throne; ſet the Crowne on your
head, put the Scepter into your hand, and planted correſpondent royall
vertues, and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies for diſcharge of the ſame in your noble
heart. So that vnder him, we acknowledge no other Soueraigne, but your
Maieſty. Our firme beleefe is, that betweene God and the King, there is no
middle, nor third perſon. To call this receiued verity into any doubt or
queſtion, among vs, is taken for conuinced hereſie; and to make thereof
ſo much as any problematicall argument, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted an odious and capitall
crime. This leſſon, Sir, we haue learned from our Predeceſſors, which
wee firmely beleeue, and diuulge all ouer, both with liuely voyce,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17731:4"/>and in writing, recommending the ſame likewiſe both by
precept and example, to all thoſe that ſhall ſucceed vs. And therefore we
doe promiſe ſo much againe vnto our humble ſelues, in the behalfe of your
Maieſty, that being vndoubtedly confirmed and reſolued of our fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
your Maieſty will propagate towards vs the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of your former edicts:
your royall eares will bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies open to heare our complaints, and peazing
equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ballance, you will be readie to doe vs iuſtice, as we wil
likewiſe be ready euery day, to plant more deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in your royall heart an
immutable and conſtant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, that wee will euer bee ready to liue and die
in the ſtate of your moſt faithfull and obedient ſeruants, and
ſubiects.</p>
            <p>Whereunto the King replied in theſe words: <hi>I thanke you all,
continue you in my good and loyall ſeruice, and be aſſured that I will be
your good King, and maintaine you in the priuiledges of my Edicts.</hi> Then
taking the letter which the Synode wrote to him, he gaue it to Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur
<hi>de Pont Chartrain,</hi> commanding him to reade the ſame, and frame an
anſwere.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17731:4"/>
            <head>THE LIFE, CARRIAGE, AND PROGRESSIONS OF THE vnworthie
Marſhall <hi>d' Ancre.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a <hi>Lynceus</hi> (but not the ſonne of
<hi>Apha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus</hi>) one of a more cleere and penetrant ſight, which
obſerued euen in the depth of the Kings noble heart, and in the ſecret
thoughts of his faithfull ſubiects, the ſighes that they daily poured
forth, before his Diuine Maieſty, to bee deliuered, together with this whole
poore Realme and Kingdome, from the tyrannie and oppreſſion, whereinto they
were reduced and brought, by the deepe ſubtilty, and inſupportable pride of
<hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chino;</hi> in whom queſtionleſſe (if <hi>Metempſycoſis,</hi>
or Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoricall tranſmigration could take place) the diuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſoule
of <hi>Aman,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Amadathi,</hi> the <hi>Agagean,</hi>
reſumed another bodie. But to the end euery one may be aduertiſed of the
true cauſe of theſe ſighes, you ſhall conceiue by this briefe recitall,
that <hi>Cochino</hi> was borne in Florence, of poore and meane place; and as
ſuch an one, grew to affect amorouſly a Ioyners daughter, who was called
<hi>Leonora Galligaia,</hi> as men ſaid; ſhe being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the firſt
as an inferiour chamber-maid, with the Princeſſe <hi>Maria de Medices,</hi>
whoſe cloſe ſtoole ſhee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes clenſed and emptied: within a
while her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſeruices, ioyned with ſome liberality of minde and
ſpirit obſerued in her, brought her to be raiſed and preferred to be in
the ſaid Princeſſe her chamber as an<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17731:5"/>attendant
gentlewoman; which Princeſſe at laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into France, to be ioyned
in marriage with <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, the ſaid <hi>Elenor</hi> came
along with her, and ſhe was alſo followed by <hi>Cochino;</hi> when
arriuing at Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles, a little boy of about twelue yeeres old, was able with
all eaſe, to carry their whole luggage and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; being a French youth,
and a Pariſian borne, who died not long ſince, of a dyſſenterie, or
bloody flux, in the ſtreet called <hi>de Beau-bourg:</hi> when the
Princeſſe came to be Queene, out of a franke and moſt noble
diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe aduanced all her followers, and peculiarly the ſaid
<hi>Elenor;</hi> who humbly requeſted her, that ſhee would permit her to
marrie the ſaid <hi>Cochino,</hi> which at laſt ſhe compaſſed, with
the Kings pleaſure and conſent. Then either of them inſinuating
themſelues more and more into the Queenes fauour, they grew to great fortunes
and meanes, by commending vnto their Maieſties di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers mens ſutes; who
hauing occaſion to ſue vnto them, were vrged by important occaſions and
buſineſſes, of what nature or quality ſoeuer. God at laſt, for our
own vnworthines, called the King to his mercy, depriuing vs of that glorious
Sun; leauing to ſucceed him, <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth, (whom God
maintaine and proſper) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then but ten yeeres old, who preſently, by
the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall voice and conſent of all France, was inueſted in the flowers
de Luce, and acknowledged for King; and the Queene his mother, a lamentable,
deſolate, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate Ladie, by the ſame generall conſent was
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed Regent. The naturall benignitie, and noble in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of this
great Queene, ſuffered her not to feare, either deceit, or trecherie, but
being her ſelfe of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted and innocent ſoule, ſhee thought euery
one had the like; eſpecially ſuch as were ſo farre fauoured, to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17731:5"/>come freely into her Maieſties preſence, and had the
credit to ſpeake to her in priuate. Now was the time, when this ambitious
<hi>Cochino,</hi> began by the inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall offices of his wiſe, to
depraue and detract from the Kings loyall and good ſeruants; for preſently
hee then cauſed <hi>Syllery</hi> the Chancellor, and his brother, to be
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed and driuen from his preſence; and vnder the cloke and colour
of Iuſtice, to take from the Parliament of Prouince, their reſplendant
Sonne, vnder this colour to propagate his ambition; and yet this preſently
not giuing him ſuch full contentment, he muſt needes take from him the
publicke Seales, for to conferre them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of his owne creatures; then hee
muſt needes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue from about the King, Mounſieur <hi>le Cheualier de
Vandoſme,</hi> his beloued Minion; then his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant
<hi>Luynes;</hi> forthwith his vigilant and carefull Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian
<hi>Erouard,</hi> and then his good Counſellors; preſently he gaue one
office to one, another to another: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, at one inſtant he caſt al
theſe Officers in a mould; the Keeper of Seales; the Secretarie of Eſtate,
and the Controller generall of the Treaſuries; by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
conteſting with the greateſt, for the place of chiefe Gentleman of the
Kings chamber, vſing all the power poſſible to marrie his daughter with
Mounſieur the Duke of <hi>Longueuill:</hi> who no waies bending to this
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, was in great danger to haue loſt his gouernment of Picardie, and
all his credit at Court, being inforced to eclipſe and retire himſelfe.
During theſe entercour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that ſage Prince, the Count <hi>de
Soiſſons</hi> was called to heauen; whoſe gouernment the Queene kept in
her owne hands, to appeaſe the great iealouſies of thoſe that were
competitors for the ſame; conſtituting therein <hi>Cochino,</hi> ſomtimes
Marqueſſe <hi>d' Ancre,</hi> and Marſhall<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17731:6"/>of France, for
her Lieutenant. Here then you ſee him Lieutenant of Normandy, being Maſter
&amp; Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the principall places in the ſame, which he forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
with Baſtions, Ditches, and Cannon, which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied thither out of the
Arſenall at Paris. But while theſe occurrents thus paſſed, he drained
the Baſtile of foureteene millions, bitterly checked that Imperiall
Parliament, about the demonſtrations of his diſorders, preuenting the
Princes and great Lords from conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and aſſembling therein. At laſt
he found a meanes that the Princes forſooke the Court, and Mounſieur <hi>le
Iay</hi> Preſident of the ſaid Parliament, the Kings moſt loyall and
truſtie ſeruant, was committed priſoner to the Caſtle of Ambois, vnder
a colourable and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit pretext: he procured that neither his Maieſtie,
nor his faithfull Counſell, gaue any eare neither to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of
Mounſier the Prince, nor to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and intimations of the other
Princes. One of which, that is to ſay, Mounſier <hi>de Vandoſme,</hi> he
cauſed to be impriſoned (but that he made a cunning and ſubtile
eſcape); ſo that by theſe meanes he laid the foundation of a dangerous
warre, and of great leuies of ſouldiers, arming neere kinſmen one againſt
another, as Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier <hi>de Guyſe</hi> againſt Mounſier <hi>de
Mayenne</hi> his couſine germaine, and thus ruinating the Kings poore
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: ſo that at laſt, by the wiſe and diſcreete cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of
my Lords the Dukes <hi>de Neuers, de Ventadour,</hi> Chancellor
<hi>Syllery,</hi> and other ancient Officers of the Crowne, a good Treatie
ſhould haue been drawne, the King being then at Tours, and the ſaid Lords
Princes at Loudun. But becauſe the ſaid <hi>Cochino</hi> perceiued, that
the power of theſe the Kings two faithfull ſeruants to his minde,
croſſed his ambitions, making rather vſe<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17731:6"/>of his owne
miniſters, and vpſtarts, whom himſelfe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Agents of a thouſand
Frankes, of whom he had to the number of eight hundred; and wonderfully
abuſing the Queenes exceeding clemencie and bountie, as alſo the feare and
iealouſie, that both by himſelfe and others he poſſeſſed her
withall, that ſhe ſhould be carefull of her ſelfe, and of the Kings
minoritie and youth: he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Mounſier the Prince to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſoner
on a thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the firſt of September, <hi>anno</hi> 1616: and ſo
conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all the reſt, vpon this, diſperſing themſelues, not
daring to returne, they were proclaimed Rebels, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted of high Treaſon,
all their goods confiſcated, (part of which came into his own hands) and then
three Armies were hereupon raiſed to take the ſpoile of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo
bring them in aliue or dead. Mounſieur <hi>de Guyſe</hi> went of the one
part, to ſeaze on Mounſieur <hi>de Neuers,</hi> whom hee
diſpoſſeſſed of many places: on the other ſide Mounſieur <hi>de
Montigny</hi> and Mounſieur the Count <hi>de Auuergne,</hi> went directly to
Soiſſons with 40 Canons; <hi>Cochino</hi> by an imprinted letter,
promiſed to the King foorthwith an Armie of fiue thouſand foote, and eight
hundred horſe, which he entertained for foure moneths at his owne charge;
ſending out in the meane while three or foure hundred Spyes, or
Intelligencers, ouer al the countrie, eſpecially into Paris, that by this
meanes he might diſcouer and know all ſuch as ordinarily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
againſt his Tyrannie, cauſing diuers gibbets to bee erected within the
citie whereupon to hang his oppoſites, though they armed themſelues but for
the Kings true and faithfull ſeruice. While all this thus paſſed, the
Kings loyall ſeruants, who ſaw their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters captiuitie, and the
vnworthie entreatie of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, being now of yeers, of greater
maturitie and ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17731:7"/>they conuented together, and began to
enter into a ſacred vnion, to ſhake off this yoke of <hi>Cochino,</hi> and
all his aſſiſtants, which aimed at the deſtruction of all the Princes,
and ſo to ſeaze on their goods (I meane not only of thoſe abſent and
withdrawne, as my Lords <hi>de Vandoſme, de Neuers, de Longueuille, de
Bouillon,</hi> and <hi>de Mayenne,</hi> but alſo of them preſent) as my
Lords the Count <hi>de Auuergne, de Guyſe, Ioinuille,</hi> the Cardinall of
Rhemes; then of my Lords the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> priſoner, and Count
<hi>de Soiſſons</hi> very young, but endued with an excellent ſpirit, and
a noble impe of great expectation and hopes, for his Prince and al France; then
of the moſt eminent Officers of the Crowne, then of <hi>Sieur Erouard</hi>
chiefe Phyſition, one moſt loyall to his King; of <hi>Sieur de Luynes,</hi>
and at laſt of the King himſelfe. All this effected, Mounſier ſhould
haue been ſeated in the Throne very young, the Queene-Mother Regent,
himſelfe Maior of the Palace, which dignitie he meant againe to re-erect; and
then in a little time, hauing all the authoritie in his owne hands, no body
oppoſing nor contradicting him, (al the race of <hi>Bourbon</hi> cleane
extinguiſhed, through the ſudden death of Mounſier the King)
<hi>Cochino</hi> ſhould then haue been mounted vpon the Throane, and then his
wife being made away by ſome priuie practice of his owne, he might haue
married whom he would at his pleaſure. Here you may ſee a well wouen web,
for the amputation whereof, God, who alwaies preſerueth this kingdome, put
into the heart of <hi>Lewis</hi> (beloued of God) the ſpirit of wiſedome
and vnderſtanding, as he did ſometimes into <hi>Salomon;</hi> and ſo
ſtrengthening the arme of <hi>Sieur de Vitry,</hi> his faithfull Gardian and
Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, cauſed it to diſcharge his iuſt choller, vpon the head of this
<hi>Salmonéas,</hi> which being too fauourably<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17731:7"/>dealt
withall, according to the opinion and iudgement of the people, when he was
buried ſecretly in the night, they diſ-interred at high noone day, and
thinking him vnworthie of buriall, they dragged his corps to the foot of Pont
neuf; there hung vp by the feete, on a gibbet he had lately erected: then they
cut off his noſe, and his eares, pluckt out his eyes, couched his head, cut
off like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his armes, and ſhamefull parts: this being done, it was
trailed againe through the ſtreetes of the Citie, beaten, and laid vpon with
cudgels, part of it burnt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his owne houſe, and ſome of it once
againe retrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and burnt the ſecond time, and what remained was at laſt
throwne into the water. Now, the longer they had been mute, no man daring to
ſpeake againſt him, the more they talked, ſung, and writ ſo loudly, and
pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, that all the ſtreetes re-echoed with the exulting ioyes and
outcries of the inhabitants. The blow was no ſooner giuen, but a miraculous
change and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was obſerued ouer all France, eſpecially in Paris;
for euery one aſſumed to himſelf a new forme, through ſuch an admirable
pleaſure and contentment. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie before <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> was
preſently by the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement diſſolued; the Lords <hi>de
Vandoſme, de Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, de Mayenne, de Longueuille,</hi> fell downe
incontinently at his Maieſties feete, who receiued them with a free and
royall heart, to the confuſion and ſhame of all <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinoes</hi>
creatures; who (at the arriuall of that graue and prudent Chancellor, whom his
Maieſtie ſent for, and reconfirmed him of his Counſell; of the Lords,
<hi>de Vair,</hi> reſtored to the keeping of the publike Seales, Preſident
<hi>Ianin,</hi> and <hi>Villeroy,</hi> together with others, who had been
formerly diſmiſſed and chaſed away by this <hi>Haman</hi>) va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,
and were diſſipated, like miſts or fogges at the<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17731:8"/>ariſing of the Suns cleere beames. <hi>Cochinoes</hi> life
(ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Marquis <hi>de Ancre,</hi> and Marſhall of France) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a
great and entire volume, to expreſſe and relate it at large, the which,
attending and expecting from the learned penne of <hi>Piere Matthew</hi> in his
Hiſtorie, I haue here abridged in as briefe a forme as poſſibly I could,
for a note and marke vnto thoſe, which may peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture heare talke but of a
parcell of his infernall ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and to be a iuſt terror to all ſuch
<hi>Nimrodes,</hi> from attempting to ſcale the heauens, and to bandy
againſt lawfull Kings, who are the annoynted of the Lord, principally
againſt ſuch ſpirits and mindes, voide of all gall or bitternes, but
clement and tractable, being of the ſame yeeres that our King <hi>Lewis</hi>
the 13 (beloued of God) is: for whom all France ought daily to pray, that he
may be preſerued, and bleſſed, with a moſt long and happie life. God
through his omnipotent holy fauour and grace, daily guard and defend him, for
vs, together with al the faithful Princes, and Officers of his Crown; guiding
and inſtructing his heart, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and propagation of his holy
Church, and the benefit and comfort of his poore people, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
